Chase Going Woodhouse Papers 1983.0009
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Chase Going Woodhouse Papers
undated, 1900-1984
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1983.0009
116 Linear Feet
Born in Victoria, British Columbia in 1890 the daughter of Seymour and Harriet Jackson Going, Chase Going Woodhouse studied at McGill University, the University of Berlin and the University of Chicago. She was employed by Smith College, U.S. Department of Agriculture, the University of North Carolina, Connecticut College before her election to the U.S. House of Representatives in 1945. For much of the remainder of her career she served as the Director's of the Auerbach Women's Service Bureau (1945-1981). Chase Going Woodhouse died in 1984 after a lifetime of dedicated public service.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
Chase Going Woodhouse donated her papers to the University of Connecticut Library in April, 1983.
Arrangement
Series I: Writings (undated, 1923-1961) contains Mrs. Woodhouse's published and unpublished articles, speeches, notes and abstracts. Most of the material dates from early in her career (ca. 1930-1945). This material illustrates Woodhouse's interests in topics such as women's occupations, trends in occupations, women and higher education, women and public affairs, equal rights, home economics, housing and standard of living. Some of the unpublished articles, specifically those on careers for women, appear to have been written for the Institute for Women's Professional Relations. This series is organized by document type. Both published and unpublished articles are arranged alphabetically by title. The speeches are arranged alphabetically by title, when that information is available or by the location at which the speech was given. The handwritten abstracts and notes, which Mrs. Woodhouse made on books and articles, are in no particular order.
Series II: Auerbach Service Bureau (undated, 1944-1976) consists of Chase Going Woodhouse's files as director of this organization. The Service Bureau was supported by the Beatrice Fox Auerbach Organization; its mission was to inform, assist, and advise Connecticut women and women's organizations. The Bureau's efforts were directed at a state level rather than the town, city or municipal level. The series is divided into eight subseries: Annual reports (1944-1976), Bureau History and Functions, Correspondence, Bureau Activities, Foreign Visitors, Photographs, Newsclipping Scrapbooks, and Meeting Attendance Books.
Annual reports are listed in chronological order from 1944 to 1976. Each file contains an annual report for that year and usually several calendars of events, meeting fliers, and upcoming events (such as trips and lectures). In addition, the annual reports list all activities, meetings, and lectures the Bureau sponsored.
Bureau History and Functions contains information on the Service Bureau itself, including the Advisory Boards, subcommittees, procedural files and information on the directors, Mrs. Woodhouse and Mrs. Harrison. In addition, this subseries contains information on the Bureau's sponsor and namesake, Mrs. Beatrice Fox Auerbach.
Correspondence contains letters written by and to Mrs. Auerbach, Mrs. Woodhouse and Mrs. Harrison. Included in this subseries is the important signatures file (prominent individuals) among which are university presidents and national figures such as Eleanor Roosevelt, Nelson Rockefeller and Dean Rusk.
Bureau Activities is the largest of the subseries. It contains information on meetings sponsored by the Service Bureau. The meetings are listed by titles in alphabetical order and topics range from Child Welfare to Education to Publicity. Several of these meetings reflect Mrs. Woodhouse's particular interests: International Issues and Foreign Students. Included, also, are Bureau projects, scholarships, and trips. One of the major projects sponsored by the Bureau, Juvenile Justice, is located in Series VII.
Foreign Visitors (1947-1965) contains information on guests who were chaperoned by the Service Bureau when they visited the Hartford, Connecticut, area. Many of these guests were visiting in conjunctions with the Committee on Leaders and Specialists, American Council of Education project sponsored by the Department of State. The visitors were from many countries and observed various activities and functions of American life.
Photographs contains images of Service Bureau representatives, foreign visitors and meeting attendees.
Newsclipping scrapbooks is comprised of approximately forty (40) scrapbooks and several files on the Bureau and its activities.
Meeting attendance books lists the coordinator's name, meeting location, date, and name of the guest lecturer for scheduled events. Also included is a guest book, which may be from Mrs. Woodhouse's home.
Series III: Trends in Occupations Project (1900-1947) contains the tables, reports and research notes of Chase Going Woodhouse for Works Progress Act (WPA) Project #2085, which she directed. The purpose of the project, according to Woodhouse, was "to make available in usable form data concerning changes in occupational distribution in the United States since 1910 (1900 when available); and to interpret those data..." from the Institute of Women's Professional Relations at Connecticut College in New London, CT. This series is further subdivided into three subseries: Tables, Reports and Reference Files.
Tables are the compilations of the Trends in Occupations Project. The 54 tables are broadly divided by occupation. Within the table, data is compiled by sex, state, census area, region, and city (population over 100,000), for 1910, 1920 and 1930.
Reports contain reports about and from the Project, including a draft of the final report. The series is arranged chronologically.
Reference Files (1900-1953, bulk 1934-1937) contains publications gathered and notes taken by Mrs. Woodhouse. The major topics in this subseries are population trends, occupation trends and standards of living. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
Series IV: Status of Women (1908-1984, bulk 1960s-1970s) contains information on women's organizations, newsletters, federal and state reports, articles and publications concerned specifically with women and the women's movement. The materials are divided into two subseries: Organizations and Publications and Topics, both are arranged alphabetically.
Organizations and Publications is a compilation of newsletters and other publications from colleges and universities, state and federal agencies, and from regional and national organizations dealing with the women's movement.
Topics consists of publications and information focused on specific areas of the women's movement. The underlying theme throughout this subseries is how these issues affect or are affected by women.
Series V: Constitutional Convention (1965, 1969) contains the documents maintained by Woodhouse from the 1965 Constitutional Convention in the state of Connecticut. Mrs. Woodhouse was co-chair of the Committee on Constitutional Resolutions and the series reflects her position more than it offers information on the Convention itself. The Committee on Constitutional Resolutions dealt with resolutions that would change the Constitution of the state. The committee's work focused on the following issues: voting rights, home rule, reapportionment, and state eminent domain.
Series VI: Public Service (1929-1982) contains documents, reports and publications produced by, or as a result of, a council, committee, group or office held by Mrs. Woodhouse. The series demonstrates the spectrum of public service positions held by Mrs. Woodhouse and reflects her personal interests. The organizations were local (Sprague, Connecticut Planning and Zoning Board), state (Connecticut Humanities Council, Citizen's Advisory Council on Safe Schools), and political. Woodhouse's service positions were held concurrently with her tenure as director of the Auerbach Women's Service Bureau. Additional positions are noted in Series VIII, subseries Commissions.
Series VII: Juvenile Justice (1951-1980) contains publications, correspondence and grant files from the Connecticut Justice Commission and Project Juvenile Justice sponsored by the Auerbach Service Bureau. The series is divided into two subseries: Meetings, workshops and symposia and Publications.
Meetings, workshops and symposia contains materials on meetings, lectures, talks and workshops held throughout Connecticut and focused on the juvenile justice system.
Publications is further divided between Auerbach publications and other. The Auerbach publications are one of the significant products of the Juvenile Justice Project. Other publications consists of those concerned with juvenile justice and published by state and national agencies.
Series VIII: Recognitions (1913-1981) contains some of the awards presented to Woodhouse during her lifetime. The series has five subseries: Awards, Photographs, Diplomas, Commissions and Invitations and Letters.
Awards is a chronological list of plaques, certificates and letters of appreciation. The awards were presented from such organizations as the National Council of Negro Women, the United States Committee for UNICEF, and the Department of State.
Photographs contain portrait and snapshot images of Mrs. Woodhouse.
Diplomas contain the Master of Arts degrees granted to Woodhouse from McGill University and Honorary degree from the University of Connecticut.
Commissions includes commissions from the Advisory Council on Community Affairs, the Commission on Connecticut's Future, and the Advisory Council for the Unemployment Compensation Act.
Invitations and Letters consists of invitations to inaugural balls (Kennedy), correspondence pertaining to her resignation from the Office of Price Stabilization, re-election materials, and a booklet from Mohegan Community College announcing the winning entry and author Chase Going Woodhouse Poetry Prize.
Biography
Born in Victoria, British Columbia in 1890 the daughter of Seymour and Harriet Jackson Going, Chase Going Woodhouse received a B.A. (1912) and M.A. (Economics, 1913) from McGill University. She studied for her Ph.D. at the University of Berlin (Germany, 1913-1914) and the University of Chicago (1915-1916) and was named a Fellow in Political Economy at the University of Chicago in 1917. Married that same year to Edward James Woodhouse, she accepted a position at Smith College, where she taught from 1917 until 1925. After three years as a Senior Economist of the Division of Economics of the Bureau of Home Economics of the U.S. Department of Agriculture (1925-1928), Woodhouse returned to academia as the Director of Personnel, Woman's College, at the University of North Carolina (1928-1934). In 1934, she accepted the position of Professor economics at Connecticut College, a position she held for ten years. From 1941-1943 she also served as the Secretary of the State of Connecticut and published a book, The Big Store, in 1943. Woodhouse was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives in 1945 and served two terms (1945-1947, 1949-1951). For much of the remainder of her career she served as the Director of the Auerbach Women's Service Bureau (1945-1981).
Chase Going Woodhouse died in 1984 after a lifetime of dedicated public service.
CHRONOLOGY
1890 Born in Victoria, British Columbia, Canada. Daughter of Seymour and Harriet Jackson Going.
1907-1908 Student at Science Hill School, Shelbyville, Kentucky.
1912 B.A. McGill University, Canada.
1913 M.A. Economics, McGill University, Canada.
1913-1914 Doctoral student at University of Berlin, Germany.
1915-1916 Doctoral student at University of Chicago.
1917 Fellow in Political Economy at the University of Chicago. Married Edward James Woodhouse, Professor of Government.
1917-1918 Assistant Professor of Economics at Smith College.
1918 Associate Professor of Economics at Smith College.
1920-1925 Professor of Economics at Smith College.
1921 Son, Noel Robert Seymour Woodhouse, born.
1925 Daughter, Margaret Wark Woodhouse, born.
1925-1928 U.S. Department of Agriculture.
1928-1934 Director of Personnel, Woman's College, University of North Carolina.
1928-1944 Established and directed the Institute of Women's Professional Relations.
1934-1944 Professor of Economics at Connecticut College.
1941-1943 Secretary of the State of Connecticut (Democrat)
1943 The Big Store.
1945-1947 Representative of the Second District (eastern) of Connecticut to the U.S. House of Representatives.
1945-1981 Director, Auerbach Women's Service Bureau.
1946-1947 Director, Women's Division, National Democratic Committee.
1949-1951 Second term as representative of the Second District of Connecticut to the U.S. House of Representatives.
1959-1963 Executive Committee, Connecticut Mental Health Association.
1960 Delegate to the U.S. Conference on Children and Youth.
1960-1971 Sprague (CT) Planning and Zoning Commission.
1961-1966 Executive Committee, National Council for Community Service to International Visitors; President (1965).
1962 Governor's Committee on Libraries, Governor's Committee on a Branch of the University in Southeastern CT.
1962-1965 State Advisory Committee on Unemployment Compensation.
1962-1969 New England Governor's Research Committee.
1963-1965 Steering Committee,
1963-1973 Board of Directors, Southeastern Connecticut Regional Planning Agency.
1964-1974 Executive Committee,
1965 Delegate, State Constitutional Convention.
1965-1966 Governor's Clean Water Task Force.
1965-1971 Chair, Sprague Planning and Zoning Commission.
1966-1967 Chair, Governor's Commission on the Status of Women.
1968-1971 Eastern Connecticut Resource, Conservation and Development Commission.
1969-1970 Department of Human Services.
1970-1971 Steering Committee, Governor's Committee on Environmental Policy.
1972 Expectation Study Group, Comprehensive Health Planning, HEW.
1973 Winslow Award, Connecticut Public Health Association.
1973-1980 Permanent Commission on the Status of Women.
1974 U.S. State Department
1975 Chair, Task Force on Housing. Chair, Commission on Connecticut's Future. Connecticut Humanities Council.
1981 Connecticut Magazine.
1982 Ella T. Grasso
1984 New Canaan, CT Alfred University Allegheny College Honorary Degrees: Albertus Magnus College Publications: University of Hartford St. Joseph's College Connecticut College Legal Rights of Children The Big Store
Custodial History
The Constitutional Convention materials (Series V) were originally donated to the Connecticut Historical Society but were transferred to the University in February, 1984. The Auerbach Service Bureau annual reports (1945-1975) (Series II), were transferred to the Library in July, 1986 by the Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe College.
Scope and Content
The Chase Going Woodhouse Papers reflect Mrs.Dr. Woodhouse's activities and interests including family and women's issues, service to the state of Connecticut and people in her community, and her professional life. Materials include correspondence, reports, speeches, articles, photographs, notes, publications, and newsletters.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
99 patches Dodd A9747
American women Dodd A9745/A10392
Book of marriage Dodd A10387
Education for Ladies Dodd A10390
Family Dodd A10394
Farmers in a changing world Dodd C10728
Few are chosen Dodd A9746
History of Asylum Hill Congregational Church Dodd C10731
I Lost Everything Dodd A9765
Law and woman's work Dodd C10205
Legacy to Wage earning women Dodd C10729
Memoirs of Mary Lyon Dodd A9748
Model City Dodd A9764
Philosophy of housekeeping Dodd A9722
On and off the floor Dodd C10732
Samuel Ferguson Dodd C10730
Television and Social Behavior, v. III Dodd C7419
Textile problems for the consumer Dodd A10384
Trained woman and the economic crisis Dodd A10383
Understanding politics Dodd A9744
Volunteer's adventures; a Union captain's record of the Civil War Dodd C10733
Why women cry Dodd A10388
Woman's best years Dodd A10386
Woman's dilemma Dodd A10385
Woman's rights under law Dodd A9739
Women in Congress Dodd A9766
Women in industry Dodd A10393
The Women's Trade Union Leagues in Great Britain and the United States of America Dodd A9733
Women who work Dodd A10389
Working mothers and the day nursery Dodd A10391
Politicians; Legislators; Monographs; Correspondence; Audio visual materials; Women; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Administrative records; Financial Records; Videocassettes; Economists; United States (nation); Notebooks; College teachers; Publications (documents); Manuscripts (document genre); Educators; Personal papers
- Series I: Writings, undated, 1923-1961
  - Published Articles
    - "An Adventure in adult education." American Unity, 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - "Character development in children of successful families." Religious Education, vol. XXV, #10., 1930 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - "The Chemical Secretary." The University Placement Review, University of Pennsylvania Quarterly, Spring, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - "College Women in the World of Work." Smith Alumna Quarterly, V. XXIV, #2, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - "College Women in the World of Work, a Stock Taking.", 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - "Comparison of schedule and account methods of Collecting data on Family Living." U.S. Department Of Agriculture. Technical Bulletin #386, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - "The Consumer and Congress." Journal of Home Economics (JHE), V. 38, # 7., 1946 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - "The Demand for College Trained Women in the United States." Journal of the American Association of University Women (JAAUW), 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - "Does Money Make the Marriage Go." Survey Graphics, v. XX, #4., 1932 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - "Economic and Social Problems of the Home." JHE, v. 20, #3., 1928 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - "The Economic Problems of the Family and What Home Economics has to offer toward Their solution." Convention of the Association of Land Grant Colleges, 1927 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - "The Economic Problems of the Home." JHE, v. 17, #9, 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - "Education—for What?" Junior League Magazine, v. XVII, #6., 1932 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - "The Field of Research on the Economic and Social Problems of the Home." JHE, v. 20, #3-5., 1928 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - "The foreign student in the United States: what's the program?" Vital Issues, v. 13, #9., 1964 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - "General principles of interprofessional relationships." Report of the National League of Nursing Education, 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - "A girl and her job." Woman's Home Companion, 1937 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - "Home economics and the new social philosophy." JHE, v. 26, #7., 1934 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - "The home economist in consumer service." Practical Home Economics, v. XVI, #10., 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - "How the Joneses do it." Survey Graphic, v. XIV, #2., 1928 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - "Jobs for our daughters." The Christian Home, v. 4, #8., 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - "A layman's reading list in economics." JHE, v. 25, #3., 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - "Managing money in successful families." JHE, v.23, #1., 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - "Married college women in business and the professions." Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, v. CXLIII., 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - "May married women teach?" JAAUW, v. XXV, #3., 1932 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - "Modern homemaking in relation to the liberal arts college for women." JAAUW, v. 19, #2., 1926 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - "Mother: general manager of the plant." The Parents' Children Magazine, 1929 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - "The new profession of homemaking." Survey Graphic, v. X, #3., 1926 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - "Occupations of members of the American Association of University Women." JAAUW, v. 21, #4., 1928 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - "Our short term international visitors: who comes and why?" Vital Issues, v. 14, #5., 1965 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
    - "Opportunities for the woman Ph.D." Independent Woman, v. 11, #4., 1932 (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - "The social science in the education of women." Progressive Education, v. 2, #4., 1925 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - "Social studies—a background for all vocations." Education, v. 60, #6., 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - "Some socializing aspects of education for homemaker." Smith Alumnae Quarterly, v. XVII, #2., 1925 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - "A Study of 250 successful families." Social Forces, v. VII, #4., 1930 (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - "Some trends in women's work." Social Forces, v. X, #4., 1938 (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - "Some trends in women's work today..." JAAUW, v. XXIX, #3., 1936 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - "The standard of living at the professional level, 1816-1817 and 1926-1927." The Journal of Political Economy, v. XXXVII, #5., 1929 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
    - "The status of the home manager today." Seventh International Management Congress, 1938 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - "The status of women." American Journal of Sociology, v. XXXV, #6., 1930 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - "A Tentative plan for a school for the social economy of the home." Social Forces, v. IV, #3., 1926 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - "Toward fair minimum wages." The Woman Worker. United States Department of Labor, Women's Bureau., 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - "Tradition and the professional woman." International Altrusan, v. XVII, #6., 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - "Vocational guidance for women." The Junior College Journal, v. VIII, #2., 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
    - "War and post-war demands for trained personnel." The Institute for Women's Professional Relations. Connecticut College, New London, Connecticut, 1943 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - "Where will women work in 1938?" Alabama College Special Bulletin on Student Career Conference, 1934 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - "The why of courses in homemaking." School and Home, v. IX, #27., 1926 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - "Women." American Journal of Sociology, v. 38, #6., 1933 (Box 3:, Folder 48)
    - "Women in industry, the family and the home." Industrial Psychology, v. 1, #4., 1926 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
    - "Women in men's jobs?" The University Placement Review, v. XI, #1., 1939 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
    - "Women of Berlin." Survey Graphic, 1948 (Box 3:, Folder 51)
    - "Women's Work and economic change." JAAUW, v. 31, # 2., 1938 (Box 3:, Folder 52)
    - Book reviews, 1941-1946 (Box 3:, Folder 53)
    - "Books by women about women." JAAUW, v. XXVIII, #4., 1935 (Box 3:, Folder 54)
    - "More books by and about women." JAAUW, v. XXVII, #4., 1934 (Box 3:, Folder 55)
  - Unpublished articles
    - "American women in today's world.", 1948 (Box 3:, Folder 56)
    - "Are women effective citizens?", 1949 (Box 3:, Folder 57)
    - "The attitude of American women toward political activity in the United States.", ca. 1960s (Box 3:, Folder 58)
    - "Changing economic conditions and the education of women.", ca. 1934 (Box 3:, Folder 59)
    - "Choosing tomorrow's job today.", undated (Box 3:, Folder 60)
    - "The contribution of economics to the problems of the consumer.", undated (Box 3:, Folder 61)
    - "Dairying in Connecticut.", 1950 [?] (Box 3:, Folder 62)
    - "Education and business.", ca. 1935 (Box 3:, Folder 63)
    - "Education and personal adjustment.", undated (Box 3:, Folder 64)
    - "Education in war and peace.", ca. 1944 (Box 3:, Folder 65)
    - "An experiment in education.", ca. 1946 (Box 3:, Folder 66)
    - "The girl and the realities of the job.", 1930s (Box 3:, Folder 67)
    - "The girl and the jobs like.", 1930s (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - "How do you do it.", undated (Box 3:, Folder 69)